这里是梵蒂冈城
This is the Vatican City.
教宗的所在地与天主教会的总部
Home to the Pope and headquarters of the Catholic Church.
对许多人来说，这里是圣洁无瑕之地，充满了祈祷与华美的教堂
To many, it's a holy and innocent place, filled with prayers and beautiful churches.
但如果我告诉你，在这光鲜外表之下
However, what if I told you that alongside this,
这座城市还藏着更为隐秘的一面呢？
the city has a much more covert side?
你看，梵蒂冈虽是世上最小的国家，其影响力却绝非如此
See, while the Vatican is the smallest country on earth, its influence is anything but.
它有时被戏称为“地球上最高效的情报机构”
It's sometimes jokingly referred to as the most effective intelligence agency on earth.
不，这并非指他们像中情局或军情六处那样运作
And no, not in the sense that they operate like the CIA or MI6,
而是以一种截然不同的方式
but rather in a much different way.
我知道这听起来很疯狂，但千真万确，而且这还不是全部
I know it sounds crazy, but it's true, and that's not even everything.
但要理解梵蒂冈情报运作的范畴，我们需要追溯其源起之时
But to understand the scope of how Vatican intelligence operates, we need to go back to when it first began.
其渊源至少可追溯至十六世纪
Its origins can be traced back to at least the 16th century,
当时天主教会正与新教英格兰发生冲突
when the Catholic Church was clashing with Protestant England.
尤其是与女王伊丽莎白一世
And more particularly, Queen Elizabeth I.
那时，欧洲因宗教改革而四分五裂
At the time, Europe was divided by the Reformation.
伊丽莎白治下的英格兰已脱离罗马，并皈依了新教
England, under Elizabeth, had broken away from Rome and embraced Protestantism.
对梵蒂冈而言，这不仅是异端邪说
For the Vatican, this wasn't just heresy.
更是一种政治上与生存上的威胁
It was a political and existential threat.
时任教宗庇护五世在1570年正式将她逐出教会
When then-Pope Pius V formally excommunicated her in 1570,
但这还不够，并认定若要对抗女王
it wasn't enough and decided that if they were to counter the Queen,
他们就需要情报来支持伊丽莎白的天主教对手，苏格兰女王玛丽
they'd need intelligence to support Mary, Queen of Scots, Elizabeth's Catholic rival.
因此根据研究，教宗监督建立了一个隐秘的
So according to research, the Pope oversaw the creation of a covert,
非正式的网络，用以监视英国宫廷并汇报其在欧洲各地的活动
informal network that could monitor the English court and report on its activities across Europe.
遗憾的是，关于那之后的事情信息寥寥无几
Unfortunately, there isn't much information on what came after that.
至少在接下来的几个世纪里是如此
At least for the next few centuries.
直到1909年，教宗庇护十世的得力助手翁贝托·贝尼尼
It was only in 1909, when Umberto Benigni, the right-hand man of Pope Pius X,
建立了一个新的间谍网络，名为“虔诚会”
set up a new network of spying, called Sodalitium Pianum,
梵蒂冈才在情报世界中扮演日益核心的角色
that the Vatican would assume an increasingly central role in the world of intelligence.
这个组织诨名为“萨皮涅尔”，是一个内部间谍网络
Informally known as La Sapiniere, this was an internal spy network.
其目标是打击教会内部的现代主义
Its goals were to combat modernism inside the church.
而我所说的现代主义，是指自由神学、圣经批判、世俗哲学之类的思想
And by modernism, I mean liberal theology, criticism of the Bible, secular philosophy, things like that.
萨皮涅尔的运作方式基本上就像一个秘密警察机构
How La Sapiniere operated was basically like a secret police.
其核心圈子不超过五十名神职人员
There was an inner circle of no more than 50 clergy.
但他们培养了一个更广泛的网络，由神父、修生和神学家组成
But they cultivated a much wider network of priests, seminarians and theologians
这些人会监视教会内任何他们认为对其保守意识形态构成威胁的人
who'd run surveillance on anyone within the church they thought were a threat to its conservative ideology.
这意味着拦截私人信件、检查书店记录以查看谁在买什么书
This meant intercepting private mail, examining the records of bookshops to see who was buying what,
跟踪嫌疑人等等
following suspects around and more.
然后他们会向贝尼尼提交报告，再由他转呈梵蒂冈
They'd then submit reports to Benigni, who forwarded them to the Vatican.
这种通讯包含密码和化名
This communication included secret codes and pseudonyms,
例如教宗庇护十世被称为“米其林夫人”
such as Pope Pius X being referred to as Lady Michelin,
而梵蒂冈国务卿，梅里·德尔瓦尔枢机则被称为“罗密小姐”
and the Vatican Secretary of State, Cardinal Merry Del Valle, as Miss Romy.
如果有人被认定有罪，他们的职业生涯基本上就算毁了
If someone was found guilty, they could basically have their career ruined.
被调查的人中甚至包括后来的教皇若望二十三世
One of the people being investigated was even Pope John XXIII,
当时他还是一位教会史教师
back when he was a teacher of church history.
但可以肯定的是，他没有被进一步追究
But it's safe to say he wasn't pursued further.
据说萨皮涅尔于1921年被教皇本笃十五世解散
La Sapiniere was said to have been dissolved in 1921 by Pope Benedict XV,
但也有人说，它至少部分存在至第二次世界大战初期
though according to others, it existed at least partly until the beginning of World War II.
不过说到战争，正是在此时梵蒂冈从拥有秘密警察
But speaking of the war, this is when the Vatican shifted from having a secret police
转变为全球情报的掮客
to becoming a global intelligence broker.
且听我解释
Let me explain.
早在1929年，梵蒂冈城通过与意大利王国签署《拉特兰条约》
Back in 1929, the Vatican City became an independent state inside Rome,
成为了罗马城内的一个独立国家
with the signing of the Lateran Treaty between them and the Kingdom of Italy.
但该条约也要求他们在所有国际事务中保持中立
But what it also did was require them to be neutral in all international affairs,
除非被请求不这样做
unless requested not to be.
身处这样的位置，尤其是在1943年罗马被德国占领期间
By being in this position, especially during when Rome was under German occupation in 1943,
使其成为少数几个能让外交官、情报机构
made it one of the few places where diplomats, intelligence agencies,
和各地神职人员秘密会面的地方之一
and clerics from all over could secretly meet.
结果，梵蒂冈就成了一个全球情报的掮客
As a result, the Vatican became like a global intelligence broker.
例如，教宗的私人秘书，罗伯特·莱伯神父
For example, the Pope's private secretary, Father Robert Leiber,
在庇护十二世与德国抵抗运动之间担任中间人
acted as the intermediary between Pius XII and the German resistance
为当时计划于1940年发动的针对德国政府的政变做准备
in the lead up to a then planned coup against the German government in 1940.
教宗会先审阅情报，然后再传递给英国
The Pope would then review the intelligence before passing it on to Britain.
他还就德军计划入侵低地三国向同盟国发出警告
He also warned the Allies about the planned invasion of the Benelux countries.
对德国人来说，他们将教宗的行为等同于间谍活动
To the Germans, they regarded the Pope's behavior as equivalent to espionage
并对这座城市进行监视
and surveilled the city.
战争结束，我们进入冷战年代后
Once the war ended and we got into the Cold War decades,
梵蒂冈的秘密行动也在此期间达到了顶峰
that's where the Vatican reached the peak of their co-vote operations.
你看，梵蒂冈认为共产主义本质上是无神论的
See, the Vatican saw communism as atheistic in nature,
说实话，通常确实如此
which is usually true to be fair.
所以这意味着他们从一开始就坚决反对它
So it meant they were firmly opposed to it from the very beginning.
他们对抗东方集团的策略最初围绕罗马一所名为“Russicum”的学校展开
Their strategy to oppose the Eastern Bloc was first centered around a school in Rome known as Russicum.
这所学校实际上成立于1929年，旨在为派往俄国服务的神父做准备
This was actually established in 1929 to prepare priests for service in Russia.
但数十年后，它承担了全新的重要使命
But it took on a whole new importance decades later,
为那些能尝试潜入铁幕后执行秘密任务的神职人员做准备
preparing clergy who could attempt clandestine missions behind the Iron Curtain.
对于像波兰或匈牙利这样已有稳固天主教基础的国家
For countries with an already established Catholic presence, such as Poland or Hungary,
目标是支持当地教会的领导层，并鼓励抵抗国家控制
the goal was to support the church's local hierarchy and encourage resistance to state control.
但在天主教几乎被赶尽杀绝的苏联
But in the Soviet Union, where Catholicism was nearly wiped out,
则是一个完全不同的挑战
it was a whole different challenge.
这里的目标仅仅是让天主教信仰存活下去
The goal here was just to keep Catholicism alive.
神父们以虚假身份和背景偷运入境
Priests were smuggled in under false identities and backstories.
弥撒在地下举行
Mass was performed underground.
关于政治氛围的报告被秘密地传送回罗马
And reports of the political atmosphere were secretly funneled back to Rome.
正是因此，根据克格勃叛逃者瓦西里·米特罗欣的说法
It was for this reason that, according to KGB defector, Vasili Mitrokhin,
克格勃将梵蒂冈视为其在海外最主要的颠覆性对手之一
the KGB viewed the Vatican as one of their primary subversive opponents abroad.
然而，当我们接近冷战末期时，事情变得更加有趣
Things got more interesting though when we get towards the end of the Cold War,
尤其是在教皇若望·保禄二世时期
especially during the time of Pope John Paul II,
他是近五百年来第一位非意大利籍教皇
the first non-Italian pope in almost 500 years,
也是一位从内部洞悉东方集团的波兰人
and a Polish man who knew the Eastern Bloc from the inside out.
他在颠覆欧洲共产主义和帮助结束冷战中的作用怎么强调都不过分
His role in toppling European communism and helping end the Cold War cannot be overstated.
最好的例子就是波兰
The best example of this was with Poland.
早在1979年，他首次以教宗身份返回他的祖国
Back in 1979, the pope made his first papal return to his home country,
当时有超过一千三百万人前来瞻仰他
where over 13 million people came to see him.
正是通过这次标志性的访问，波兰人不再恐惧
It was through this iconic visit that Poles stopped being afraid,
反而备受鼓舞
and became inspired instead.
由此诞生了“团结工会”运动
It was from this that the birth of the Solidarity Movement,
一个广泛的反共社会运动和工会组织
a broad anti-communist social movement and trade union, was formed.
正如该运动的领导者及最终的总统莱赫·瓦文萨所说，没有他
Without him, as the leader of the movement and eventual president Lech Wałęsa put it,
这一切都不可能实现
it wouldn't have been possible.
但这仅仅是个开始
But this was just the beginning.
1981年12月13日
On December 13th, 1981,
波兰政府宣布戒严，试图对抗日益壮大的运动
the Polish government declared martial law in an attempt to counter the growing movement.
这导致梵蒂冈与中情局联手，以推翻共产主义政府
This led to the Vatican teaming up with the CIA to bring down the communist government.
这么说很疯狂，但请听我解释
It's a crazy thing to say, but let me explain.
不过首先，我想提一下，黄金和白银在2025年迎来了爆发性的一年
But first, I want to mention that gold and silver are having a breakout year in 2025,
前方广告，请空降8:50
言归正传，梵蒂冈与中情局合作的原因如下
Anyways, this is why the Vatican teamed up with the CIA.
美国出于地缘政治原因反对共产主义，而教会则是出于精神原因
The US opposed communism for geopolitical reasons, and the church for spiritual ones.
但俗话说，敌人的敌人就是朋友
But as the saying goes, the enemy of my enemy is my friend.
教皇与总统在八十年代期间会晤了四次
The Pope and president met four times throughout the 80s,
而此前的总统没有一位超过一次
while no previous president had done so more than once.
从第一次会晤开始，谈话就围绕着波兰和东欧展开
From the very first meeting, the talk centered around Poland and Eastern Europe.
我们知道这一点，因为里根图书馆有所提及
We know this because the Reagan Library mentions it.
但在表面之下，他们其实有着更深层的关系
But beneath the surface, they actually had a much deeper relationship.
前中情局副局长弗农·沃尔特斯在八十年代期间拜访了教皇近十二次
The former deputy director of the CIA, Vernon Walters, visited the Pope almost a dozen times in the 80s,
根据前美国驻教廷大使威廉·A·威尔逊的说法——他充当了他们之间的联络人
acting as their liaison, according to the former US ambassador to the Holy See, William A. Wilson.
他们协调了联合行动，中情局为团结工会运动提供了价值数百万美元的秘密援助
They coordinated joint operations, where the CIA would fund millions of dollars worth of covert aid to the Solidarity Movement,
从印刷机和通讯设备，到支持罢工的现金
from printing presses and communications equipment, to cash to support the strikes.
据著名的水门事件记者卡尔·伯恩斯坦透露
They were then smuggled into Poland via clergy and agents,
这些物资随后通过神职人员和特工被偷运到波兰
according to the famous Watergate journalist Karl Bernstein.
此时梵蒂冈的对外情报机构甚至有了一个诨名
There was even an unofficial name for the foreign intelligence agency of the Vatican at this point.
“实体”
The Entity.
虽然这显然未经证实，但已有相关书籍问世
While it's obviously unconfirmed, there's been books written about it,
而路易吉·波吉枢机，有时被称为“教皇的间谍”，据说曾掌管该机构
and Cardinal Luigi Poggi, sometimes called the Pope's spy, was said to have run it.
同时，在情报方面，两国共享信息
Meanwhile, on the intel side, the two countries shared information.
时任国务卿亚历山大·黑格甚至说
With then-Secretary of State Alexander Haig even saying that,
梵蒂冈的情报“绝对比我们的更好、更快”
the Vatican's information was absolutely better and quicker than ours.
最终，梵蒂冈与中情局在八十年代维持团结工会运动生存的联盟
Eventually, the Vatican and CIA alliance of keeping the Solidarity Movement alive during the 1980s
导致了波兰人民共和国于1989年垮台
led to the collapse of the Polish People's Republic in 1989,
以及随后波兰第三共和国的崛起
and the rise of the Third Republic of Poland,
团结工会在几十年来首次的半自由选举中获得了权力
where Solidarity gained power in the first semi-free elections in decades.
它的突破在东欧引发了多米诺骨牌效应
Its breakthrough set off a domino effect across Eastern Europe,
一个又一个共产主义政权开始相继倒台
as one communist regime began to fall after the other.
“这堪称有史以来最伟大的秘密结盟之一”
This was one of the greatest secret alliances of all time,
里根的首位国家安全顾问理查德·艾伦如是说
according to Reagan's first national security adviser, Richard Allen.
同样值得注意的是，我提到的所有这些关键政府人物
It's important to also note that all these key administration people I've mentioned,
威尔逊、黑格、沃尔特斯、艾伦，甚至当时的中情局局长威廉·凯西
Wilson, Haig, Walters, Allen, and even then-CIA director William Casey,
都是虔诚的罗马天主教徒
were all devout Roman Catholics.
他们将美梵关系视为一个“神圣同盟”
They regarded the US-Vatican relationship as a holy alliance.
中情局因此甚至曾经有个绰号叫“天主教情报局”
The CIA even used to have the nickname the Catholic Intelligence Agency for this reason.
冷战结束后，坦白说，描述梵蒂冈情报的来源变得稀少得多
After the Cold War ended, sources describing Vatican intelligence became much scarcer, to be honest.
但仍有其存在的迹象
But there were still signs of it.
例如，1997年，比利时议会将“主业会”列入危险宗教派别名单
For example, in 1997, the Belgian parliament replaced Opus Dei on a list of dangerous religious sects,
但之后在全球面临巨大争议，并未采纳该提议
but afterwards faced major backlash worldwide and didn't adopt it.
背景介绍一下，“主业会”，于1929年在西班牙成立
The Opus Dei, for context, was founded in Spain in 1929,
其使命是帮助普通人在日常生活中找到上帝
with a mission to help ordinary people find God in their daily life.
但在1982年，它获得了“属人监督团”的独特地位
But in 1982, it received the unique status of a personal prelature,
这意味着它只对教皇负责，可以独立于地方主教运作
meaning that it answered only to the Pope and could operate independently of local bishops.
这为其提供了一个全球性的自主运作框架，在教会历史上极为罕见
This gave it a global framework for autonomous operation, rarely granted in church history.
关于它的阴谋论层出不穷
There have been many conspiracies about it,
从支持拉丁美洲到西班牙的独裁统治不一而足
ranging from supporting dictatorships in Latin America to Spain.
它还是一个极其神秘的组织，这也无甚帮助
It doesn't help either that it's an extremely secretive organization,
其成员甚至不会公开自己是其中一员
where its members literally don't identify themselves as being part of.
但这些阴谋论是真是假，还是纯属夸大，都难以判断
But whether the conspiracies are true or just exaggeration is hard to tell.
但我猜想，真相至少介于两者之间
But I'd assume it's at least somewhere in the middle.
用托马斯·图罗夫斯基的话来说——
In the words of Thomas Turovsky,
他是一名波兰共产主义情报官员，曾作为间谍渗透梵蒂冈
a Polish communist intelligence officer who infiltrated the Vatican as a spy,
后来最终成为派驻该国的外交官
before eventually becoming a diplomat to the country,
“梵蒂冈的间谍比《007》里的还多”
there were more spies in the Vatican than in James Bond films.
梵蒂冈的间谍活动有许多不为人知之处是必然的
It's inevitable that much about the Vatican's spycraft is unknown,
而且很多将永远是个谜
and much will forever remain so.
但可以肯定的是，每隔几个月就会有惊人的内幕被曝光
But there are some crazy revelations being brought to light every few months, that's for sure.
当然，梵蒂冈不仅是进行间谍活动的一方，它也是间谍活动的目标
Of course though, the Vatican isn't just the one doing the spying, it's also the target of it.
美国，更具体地说是国家安全局，被曝出于2013年窃听了梵蒂冈的通讯
The US, and more specifically the NSA, were revealed to have tapped Vatican communications in 2013.
而在教皇选举会议期间，也就是枢机团集会选举新教皇之时
And during papal conclaves, which is when the College of Cardinals convenes to elect a new pope,
梵蒂冈会进入全面的反情报模式
the Vatican goes into full counterintelligence mode.
会议地点西斯廷教堂
The location of it, the Sistine Chapel,
会由梵蒂冈的宪兵队进行清扫，检查有无隐藏的麦克风或摄像头
is swept for hidden microphones or cameras by the Vatican's Jean de Marie Corps,
宪兵队也就是其安全部队
which is the security force.
会部署信号干扰器以阻断手机、无线网络和无线电传输
Signal jammers are deployed to block cell phones, Wi-Fi and radio transmissions.
甚至枢机主教住所的窗户都会被封锁
Even the windows of the cardinal's residences are blocked.
然而，这并不能阻止外国情报机构试图干预
Yet, this doesn't stop foreign intelligence agencies from trying to interfere.
赌注实在太高了
The stakes are simply too high.
教皇的影响力如此之大，各国政府不可能不想在决定谁将赢得选举中占得先机
And the pope has too much influence for governments not to look for a leg up in determining who will win the election.
总之，目前梵蒂冈的情报本质上就是其外交手腕
Anyways, for now, the Vatican's intelligence is essentially its diplomacy.
与184个国家保持着外交关系，教皇使节派驻在几乎每个国家的首都
With 184 states maintaining relations, papal envoys posted in nearly every capital,
以及数百万散布在全球各地的神职人员和俗职人员
and millions of clergy and lay workers scattered across the globe,
他们仍然能接触到可与任何政府匹敌的信息流
they still have access to information flows that rival any government.
从这个意义上说，梵蒂冈仍然运作着世界上最广泛的人力情报网络之一
In that sense, the Vatican still operates one of the broadest human intelligence networks in the world.
只是这个网络建立在教牧关系之上，而非传统的间谍
Just one built on pastoral ties rather than traditional spies.
至少这是我们所了解的
At least that's what we're aware of.
感谢您的观看，别忘了关注以获取更多此类内容
Thank you for watching, and don't forget to subscribe for more content like this.
咱们下期见
I'll see you in the next one.